Shruthi Hiremath

Updated on July 23, 2024

Computational Behavior Analysis Lab,

School of Interactive Computing, Georgia Institute of Technology, 756 W Peachtree St NW,

Atlanta, GA 30308

Email: shiremath9@gatech.edu; hiremath.shruthi@gmail.com

Mobile: +1-470-265-163

Website Google Scholar

Research Interest

My research interest broadly focuses on building novel activity recognition pipelines for nearable sensing devices. I focus on activity monitoring in smart homes, by observing data collected from residents in smart homes using nearable sensors. As such I propose a "lifespan" of a human activity recognition system in smart homes, which includes (a) initial bootstrapping procedure - aimed at 'jump-starting' the activity recognition system in the home, with minimal supervision from the resident; (b) updating and extending the activity recognition system - aimed at improving the recognition capabilities of the initial bootstrapped system; (c) routine assessment - aimed at behavior monitoring of residents over extended periods of observation.

Education

| Aug '18 - Dec '24 (expected) | Ph.D. in Computer Science | Atlanta, GA |
|------------------------------|--|----------------|
| • | Georgia Institute of Technology | |
| | Thesis: "Deriving Bespoke Human Activ- | |
| | ity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes" | |
| | Doctoral Committee: Thomas Plötz | |
| | (Advisor), Sonia Chernova, Diane Cook, | |
| | Gregory Abowd, Uichin Lee | |
| Aug '15 - May '17 | M.S. in Computer Science | Atlanta, GA |
| | Georgia Institute of Technology | |
| Aug '10 - July '14 | B.Tech in Computer Science | Vellore, India |
| | VIT UNIVERSITY | |

Publications

Refereed Conference, Journal and Workshop Papers

- P1. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2024). Game of LLMs: Discovering Structural Constructs in Activities using Large Language Models. Arxiv (Under Review).
- P2. Sourish Dhekane, Megha Thukral, **Shruthi K. Hiremath**, Harish Haresamudram and Thomas Plötz.(2024). Layout Agnostic Human Activity Recognition in Smart Homes through Textual Descriptions Of Sensor Triggers (TDOST). Arxiv (Under Review).

- P3. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2024).Maintenance Required: Updating and Extending Bootstrapped Human Activity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes. The 6th International Conference on Activity and Behavior Computing (ABC).
- P4. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2023). The Lifespan of Human Activity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes. Sensors 2023, 23(18), 7729; DOI: 10.3390/s23187729
- P5. Shruthi K. Hiremath, Yasutaka Nishimura, Sonia Chernova and Thomas Plötz.(2022). Bootstrapping Human Activity Recognition Systems for Smart Homes from Scratch. Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT), 6(3), 1-27; DOI: 10.1145/3550294
- P6. Yulai Cui, **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz (2022). ROAR: Reinforcement Learning Based Online Active Learning for Human Activity Recognition. In 2022 International Symposium on Wearable Computers (ISWC) (pp. 2327); DOI: 10.1145/3544794.3558457
- P7. Mindy Scheithauer, **Shruthi K. Hiremath**, Audrey Southerland, Agata Rozga, Thomas Plötz, Chelsea Rock, Nathan Call (2022). Feasibility of accelerometer technology with individuals with autism spectrum disorder referred for aggression, disruption, and self-injury. Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders, 98, 102043; DOI: 10.1016/j.rasd.2022.102043
- P8. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz. (2021). On the Role of Context Length for Feature Extraction and Sequence Modeling in Human Activity Recognition. In 2021 International Symposium on Wearable Computers (ISWC) (pp. 13-17); DOI: 10.1145/3460421.3478825
- P9. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Thomas Plötz.(2020). Deriving effective human activity recognition systems through objective task complexity assessment. Proceedings of the ACM on Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT), 4(4), 1-24; DOI: 10.1145/3432227
- P10. Shruthi K. Hiremath, Pallavi Chandra, Anne M. Joy, and B. K. Tripathy (2015). Neighborhood rough set model for knowledge acquisition using MapReduce. International Journal of Communication Networks and Distributed Systems (IJCNDS), 15(2-3), 212-234; DOI: 10.1504/IJC-NDS.2015.070975
- P11. **Shruthi K. Hiremath** and Govinda K(2014). Rainfall Prediction Using Artificial Neural Network. International Journal Applied Engineering Research, 9, (pp. 21243-21254).

Professional Experience

Aug '18 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant

Georgia Institute of Technology

I developed data-driven technologies for wearable and nearable based application scenarios to build deployable human activity recognition systems, with a focus on providing health monitoring.

May - July '16

Data Science Intern

ADP

My work involved development of data analysis procedures to analyze and gather insights from collected payroll data.

Aug '14 - July '15

Software Developer

Deloitte USI (Hyderabad, India)

I was involved in building a tool that served as an interface between end users and project management activities (PMC) aimed as reducing the number of manual tickets raised for changes to a project team. The tool successfully contributed to a 70% reduction in costs associated with handling tickets, thereby achieving significant cost savings.

Teaching Experience

Teaching Assistant

| | reaching Assistant | |
|---------------|--|----------------------|
| Summer | CS 6601: Artificial Intelligence | Georgia Institute of |
| '19, '20, '21 | | TECHNOLOGY |
| Summer '22 | CS 7470: Mobile & Ubiquitous Computing | Georgia Institute of |
| | | TECHNOLOGY |
| Fall '16, '17 | CS 4400: Database Systems | Georgia Institute of |
| | | Technology |

Funding

2010

2020

| 2019 - 2020 | Georgia | Cimicai | and | 1ran | Siationai | Science |
|-------------|----------|---------|------|------|-----------|---------|
| | Alliance | Grant | (PI: | Dr. | Thomas | Plötz), |

Commis Clinical and Thomslational Science

\$15,000 [Read More].

Optimizing context length for improved ac-Lead Researcher

tivity recognition in wearable sensing.

2018 - 2019 Pilot Grant from NIH via Georgia Institute

of Technology (PI: Dr. Thomas Plötz)

Analyzing the feasibility of using acceleromenters to identify episodes of server behavior in youth on the Autism Spectrum Disor-

der (ASD)

2022 - 2024 Collaboration with KDDI Corporation (PI:

> Thomas Plötz and Dr. Dr. Sonia

Chrernova)

Novel Human-in-the-Loop Learning for re- LEAD RESEARCHER

alization of real-world AI

LEAD RESEARCHER

Awards and Recognitions

| 2023 | N^2 Women Young Research Fellowship (\$1000), |
|------------------|--|
| | Percom 2023 |
| 2022 | Student Travel Grant (\$500), Ubicomp 2022 (by |
| | Georgia Institute of Technology) |
| 2021 | N ² Women Young Research Fellowship (\$1000), |
| | Ubicomp 2021 |
| 2019 | Imlay pre-proposal selected, Georgia Tech |
| 2015, 2018, 2021 | Grace Hopper Scholar, Georgia Tech |
| 2014 | Merit Scholar, VIT University |

Invited Talks

| 2022 | ROAR: Reinforcement Learning Based Online Active Learning for Human Activity Recognition @ |
|------|--|
| | Ubicomp |
| 2022 | Bootstrapping Human Activity Recognition Sys- |
| | tems for Smart Homes from Scratch @ Ubicomp |
| 2021 | Deriving effective human activity recognition sys- |
| | tems through objective task complexity assessment |
| | @ Ubicomp |
| 2021 | On the Role of Context Length for Feature Extrac- |
| | tion and Sequence Modeling in Human Activity |
| | Recognition @ Ubicomp |
| 2018 | Detecting severe behavior episodes in youth on the |
| | Autism Spectrum Disorder @ Georgia Tech |

Professional Service

| | Reviewer |
|-------------|--|
| 2018 - 2024 | ACM Interactive, Mobile, Wearable and Ubiquitous Technologies (IMWUT) |
| 2024 | Ubicomp Posters and Demos |
| 2024 | UbiComp/ISWC 2024 Workshop on AI-infused Physical Systems |
| 2024 | Nordic Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (NordiCHI) |
| 2023 | Workshop on Ubiquitous and Multi-domain User Modeling (UMUM) |
| 2022 | International Conference on Pervasive Computing and Communications (Percom) |
| 2021 | ACM Special Interest Group on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (SIGKDD) |
| | Program Committee Member |
| 2023 | Served on the Program Committee for 'The Second Workshop on Ubiquitous and Multi-domain User Modeling (UMUM2023)'. Held in Conjunction with PerCom 2023. [Read More] |

Community Service

| 2018 - present | Mentor, Georgia Tech: mentored undergraduate |
|----------------|--|
| | and graduate student interested in research |
| 2023 | N ² Women Event, Percom 2023 |
| 2022 | Organizing Committee (Web Chair), Ubicomp |
| | 2022 |
| 2021 | N ² Women Event, Ubicomp 2021 |
| 2020 - 2023 | Social Chair, Ubicomp Lab @ Georgia Tech |
| 2015 - 2022 | Volunteer, India Club @ Georgia Tech |
| 2010 - 2014 | Core Member, Robotics Club @ VIT University |